#山东·青岛
Qingdao, Shandong
#真的是特别冷
It's really cold
#我都穿上羽绒服了
I have to wear my down jacket
#今天呢 咱们到菜市场这一边
Today we come to this market
#买一只烤鸡来吃（目标：烤鸡）
To buy a roast chicken (Target: Roast chicken)
#这家烤鸡店 听说特别火爆
It's said that this roast chicken shop is extremely famous
#一天只营业4小时
Opens only 4 hours a day
#如果说 来晚了 可能就没有了
The chicken may be sold out if you come too late
#我们要赶快走了
We need to hurry up
#刚到市场门口 你就能闻到香味
You can smell the fragrance as soon as you arrive at the market entrance
#我感觉不用地图 也能够找到它
I think I can find it without using a map
#哇 天呐 这么多人排队
My god... So many people in the line
#得什么时候才能够吃得上
How long do I have to wait before I can buy one?
#今天有这么多人排队
The reasons why there are so many people today...
#一方面可能是因为 周一不开门
On the one hand, they don't work on Monday
#还有一个就是
On the other hand
#看到有这么多人排队 很多路过的人
With so many people waiting in the line, many people who just pass by
#可能也加入了排队的大军
may also have joined the line
#在这儿买烤鸡 可能半天不会动一步
You may not be able to take one step forward for a long time
#因为它这边是出一锅 卖一锅
Because they start to sell one pot (of chicken) only when it is ready
#如果说 烤不出来的话
If the whole pot is not ready yet
#我们仍然要站在原来的位置
We still need to stand where we are
#15分钟了 我们迈出了历史性的一步
It has been 15 minutes. We are taking a historical step
#总算向前走了一点
Finally one step forward
#还有没有鸡了
Is there whole chicken left?
#全鸡腿了
We only have chicken legs now #这里感觉不算是drumstick...
#没有鸡了
#全鸡腿了
The whole chickens are all sold out
We only have chicken legs now
#刚才老板从这个窗口告诉了我们
The shopkeeper just told us from this window
#一个不幸的消息
A piece of bad news
#今天没有烤鸡了 没有整个的烤鸡了
The roast chickens are sold out today. The whole roast chickens are sold out
#全都是鸡腿了
They only have chicken legs now
#排了老半天 竟然等待我的就是鸡腿
#目标转为：鸡腿
I have been waiting for years but what awaits me is just chicken leg
Target changed: Chicken leg
#大姐 这个鸡腿怎么卖
Sister, how much is the chicken leg?
#29一斤
#都一样的
-29 yuan per Jin (58 yuan/kg)
-The same price (as roast chicken)
#一个大约多少重
#十块多
-How heavy is each one?
-More than 10 yuan
#烤鸡是一只都没了
The roast chickens are all sold out
#那给我拿3个鸡腿吧
Then give me three chicken legs, please
#3个
#46块6
Three
46.6 yuan
#看 支付宝过去了
See? I've paid with Alipay
#咱们排了差不多半个多小时吧
We have been waiting in line for about half an hour
#一只鸡都没有剩下 就只剩鸡腿了
No chicken was left. There were only chicken legs
#我们是买了3个鸡腿 花了46块钱
It took us 46 yuan to buy three chicken legs
#走吧 我们要去吃鸡腿了
Let's go and enjoy the chicken legs!
#天气这么冷
With the weather being so cold
#拿着一个热热的鸡腿 还是感觉很幸福的
It feels awesome with such a hot, freshly-made chicken leg in hand
#咱们买的鸡腿是花了46块钱
We spent 46 yuan on three chicken legs
#也就是说 一个鸡腿是15块钱
that is, 15 yuan for each
#第一次买这么贵的鸡腿了
This is my first time to buy such an expensive chicken leg
#最近猪肉涨价 什么肉都跟着涨价
Recently pork is getting really expensive. So is the other meat
#15块钱一个鸡腿 应该个头不小吧
It's supposed to be a large one at 15 yuan #请检查这里
#咱们打开来看一看
Let's open it and take a look
#哇
#开饭了
Wow
Time to enjoy!
#青岛的妖风太厉害了
The wind in Qingdao is too strong
#我们决定临时转移阵地
We decide to move to another place
#从刚才的地方到现在的地方
From the previous place to where we are now
#因为实在是太饿了
Since we are sooo hungry
#现在只剩下一个鸡腿了
There is only one chicken leg left
#那两个鸡腿已经被我们消灭干净了
#我好孤独
The other two have been eaten up already
I am so lonely
#它这个鸡腿就是
This chicken leg is...
#就是你打开袋子的那一刻 就感觉到
The moment you open the bag, you can feel
#它的烤鸡的味道很浓郁
a strong scent of roast chicken
#它在袋子里 独自芬芳
In the bag, alone, but fragrant
#你也能看到 鸡腿是很大个的
You can also see that the chicken legs are really large
#外面是烤的皮 有点褶皱了
The roasted skin outside... is kinda wrinkled
#而且是微黄色的 就像抹了蜂蜜一样
The color is slightly gold... like with honey
#咱们是透过它褶皱的外皮
Looking through its wrinkled skin, we can see
#看它鸡腿的本身
the meat inside
#你会发现它里面的鸡腿肉 好嫩
You will find it so tender inside
#鸡腿有个特点 拿出来的时候也能发现
You can find another characteristic of this chicken leg when you take it out
#它的汤汁 顺着皮 一直朝下流
The juice inside flows down along the skin
#凭感官 也是觉得它是柔嫩多汁的
You can feel that it is tender and juicy
#你看
Look
#它里面的鸡腿肉 就是一丝丝的
The meat inside is.. slices of
#柔嫩的鸡腿肉
tender and soft meat
#其实 你要说鸡腿
Actually, when talk about a chicken leg (drumstick)
#可能这个是意义上的鸡腿吧
Maybe this is the "real" chicken leg
#但是它又加了这么多的肉
But (this one is) with so much additional meat
#这份鸡腿吃起来 鸡肉是更好吃的
In this chicken leg, the meat inside tastes better (than the skin)
#为什么呢 因为它的鸡肉的咸度是正好的
The reason is that the saltiness of the meat is within an appropriate range #这个表达是不是太academic了。。。
#那你说 鸡皮在外面 它会更咸
The skin is saltier since it's outside
#所以说 鸡皮不如鸡肉好吃
So the skin is not as delicious as the meat
#还有一点就是
Another point is
#它里面的鸡腿肉没有变的很柴
The meat inside is not getting dry and chewy
#因为里面 汤水 汤汁足够多
Because it's juicy enough inside
#吃起来会让你觉得鸡肉 肉嫩多汁
You can feel that the chicken is so tender and juicy
#如果说买回家的话
So if you take it back home
#最爽的应该还是
The best choice must be
#直接上嘴啃吧
Taking a big bite #外带字幕：带走 Take it away （这里意义略不明确）
#山东·济南
Jinan, Shandong
#行了
Ok
#你好 要那个菠菜
Hello. I would like some spinach
#豆角
Beans
#在这儿吃
Eat here
#米饭
Rice
#两个
Two bowls
#要辣还是不辣
Spicy or not?
#要微辣
Slightly spicy
#要一个肉 然后 菠菜 豆角 再要个菜花
I would like some meat, spinach, beans, and broccoli
#可以了
Okay
#多少钱
How much
#一共
In total
#30元
30 yuan
#把子肉多少钱了
How much is the "Ba zi rou" (stewed pork belly)?
#肉都30多块钱一斤了
Pork is more than 30 yuan/Jin now
#过去了 30块钱
That's in the past. 30 yuan
#肉 你买 你买得35元一斤
Now it's about 35 yuan/Jin
#咱们这是点了菠菜 豆角 菜花
We have ordered spinach, beans, and broccoli
#还有一个把子肉
And a slice of "Ba zi rou"
#现在肉太贵了 刚才大哥说
Now pork is just too expensive. The bro just said that
#咱们要的这一个把子肉 现在是8元一个
This "Ba zi rou" here is 8 yuan/piece now
#他刚才还加了一句
He added that
#如果说 你们去买猪肉
If you go to buy some pork now
#可能已经到了35块钱一斤了
The price might have increased to 35 yuan/Jin
#现在来吃猪肉 可能是赚了吧
Now we might be making money now
#你看 后面都坐满了
Look. People behind are filling up this place
#都是来吃肉的
They are all coming for meat #外加：可爱如我 I am so lovely
#把子肉是可以分辣的和不辣的
You can choose from spicy and non-spicy "Ba zi rou"
#咱们是要的一个微辣的
We ordered one piece of slight spicy meat
#还有一点我发现 这边的
Another thing I noticed is that
#豆角真的辣到让你觉得想吃饭
The beans here are so spicy that you want to eat more rice
#豆角上面有辣椒 这种干炝的辣椒
There's chili on the beans... Such fried chili
#还有白芝麻
and white sesame
#真的是吃起来特别的香
It tastes really nice
#我本来是来吃肉的
Initially I came for the meat
#没想到被干煸豆角圈粉了
But I've become a fan of the fried beans
#肉其实不算大吧 看起来
The piece of meat is not large actually
#把子肉外皮是这种糖色
The outer surface of the meat looks like caramel
#轻轻地把它碾一下
Let's crush it a little bit
#拌米饭来吃
and stir with the rice
#这个猪皮感觉很弹口
The pork skin is chewy
#Q弹Q弹的
Elastic and chewy
#而且看起来晶莹剔透的
Seems to be bright and transparent
#肥瘦相间
Fat and lean meat in between each other
#嚼一口 好香啊
Take a bite. Tastes awesome!
#它这个把子肉最大的特点就是入味
The most special thing about the meat is that the flavor is totally absorbed inside
#而且是辣的 咱们是第一次吃辣的把子肉
And it's spicy. This is our first time to taste spicy "Ba zi rou"
#这个肉吃起来一点都不柴
The meat is not dry at all
#它的肥肉不会让你觉得腻
The fat doesn't make you feel greasy
#瘦肉呢 炖的比较软烂
The lean meat is relatively soft
#进到嘴中 嚼起来不会有什么样的负担
Such that you don't have a hard time chewing it
#不爱吃肉呢
If you don't enjoy eating meat #外加：被嫌弃了 I am frowned!
#来吃把子肉 不一定要来吃肉
You don't have to eat meat if you come for "Ba zi rou"
#也可以来吃这个肉汤
You can enjoy the soup alternatively
#就是不管你要不要肉
I mean, no matter if you order meat or not
#都可以给你来点肉汤（浇米饭上）
You can have some soup added to your rice
#汤汁可能比肉 更下饭
The soup might goes with the rice even better than the meat
#咱们来的时候 正好赶上别人下班
We arrived here when other people just got off their work
#所以这个小房子 显得略微有些拥挤
So this small house appears to be somewhat crowded
#还是能够随便找几个座位 坐下来
But you can still find a seat, sit down
#好好吃一顿饭
And have a decent meal
#有没有发现 人越多
Have you found that, with more people in the restaurant
#你可能会吃得越香呢
You may feel that your meal is more delicious?
#大哥 这个把子肉开多久了
Bro, how long has this restaurant been running?
#10来年了
More than 10 years
#一直是您在做吗
Have you been running it from the beginning?
#一直就我在做的
Yes
#在这边做
Working in my restaurant here
#我看咱这边是没有厨房 直接肉
I noticed that there is no kitchen here. The meat is
#拿锅 拿桶端过来的
directly brought here with pots and buckets
#俺有厨房
I have a kitchen actually
#有厨房
I have a kitchen
#厨房不在这里
The kitchen is not here
#不在这边
Not around here
#有的把子肉在店里做 有的也不在店里做
Some of the meat is cooked in the restaurant. Some is not
#猪肉涨价对把子肉的生意有没有影响
Now that the pork is getting expensive. Is there an impact on "Ba zi rou" business?
#俺没有
No, not on mine
#也没有
No?
#俺卖的不贵 俺卖8块钱它贵吗
I don't sell it at a high price. 8 yuan/slice is not expensive at all
#8块钱 9块钱
8 yuan or 9 yuan
#以前也差不多吧
It's close to the previous price
#差不多
Not much difference
#涨价没 最近
Have you increased your price recently?
#涨了 涨了两块钱
Yes. I raised it by 2 yuan
#光要肉成9块了
You need to spend 9 yuan if you just want a slice of meat
#无所谓了 肉不挣钱 菜挣点钱也行
It doesn't matter. If I can't make money from pork, I can make money from other dishes
#是
Yep
#你得护着让老客户吃上 对吧
You need to care about your regular customers, right?
#对 对
Yes that's true
#一天 能卖多少斤猪肉
How much pork can you sell each day?
#100多斤
More than 100 Jin
#也可以了
That's a considerable amount
#每天买肉就3千多
I spend more than 3,000 yuan on buying raw meat
#4千
or 4,000
#一天4桶肉
4 buckets of meat each day
#一桶也有汤多汤少的时候
Sometimes there's more soup in the bucket
#原来有人说6桶肉呢
Someone calculated that we sell 6 buckets every day
#6桶的话 连汤带肉的
In that case, the soup is taken into consideration
#没有汤 可能6桶就剩两桶
Maybe we only sell 2 buckets without soup
#吃完还是有点撑的
I feel stuffed after this meal
#关 注
#雪 鱼 探 店
Subscribe to
"Xue Yu Tan Dian"